Pamela Kramer Papers RG.009
Poly Archives & Special Collections at Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology
Guide to the Pamela Kramer Papers, 1978 - 1999
Bulk, 1978-1995
1970-1999
RG.009
Poly Archives & Special Collections at Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology
2.0 Linear feet 2 boxes
Pamela Kramer began working at Polytechnic University in 1972 as a psychology instructor in the Humanities and Social Sciences Department. Over the course of her career at Polytechnic, she was an assistant professor, associate professor, Director of Women's Programs, and Assistant Provost for Freshman Studies. Her research initially dealt primarily with psycholinguists and developmental psychology, though she eventually came to focus on women and minorities in science. She planned, implemented, and directed numerous programs while at Poly, all aimed at helping women and minorities succeed in the engineering field.
Kramer, Pamela
Kramer-Koehler, Pamela
Biographical/Historical note
Pamela Kramer began her long career at Poly in 1972 as a Psychology instructor, two years after completing her Masters in Education and Developmental Psychology at Tufts University. After earning her PhD in Psycholinguistics in 1973, Kramer was promoted to an Assistant Professorship position in 1974. Over the course of her career at Polytechnic, Kramer also served the Director of Women’s Programs (1981- 1985) and as Department Chair of Social Sciences (1985- 1990). Kramer also planned, executed, directed, and evaluated numerous grant funded activities and programs focusing on women and minorities in the science and engineering fields, including the Careers in Research for Minority Scholars program, funded by the National Science Foundation and the Department of Defense Office of Naval Research, reentry programs for women in polymer sciences and other engineering fields, and the Gateway Program at Polytechnic University. In 1991 Kramer earned the position of Assistant Provost for Freshman Studies and was promoted to full professor in 1996. She died in Brooklyn on February 18, 1999.
Scope and Contents note
This collection contains documents relating to the research and grant programs designed and directed by Kramer, publications, and biographical information, including her CV and records detailing her recommendation and eventual appointment to full professorship. The files also contain grant proposals to the National Science Foundation and the Department of Education for projects concerning museum and university based learning and helping minority girls acquire computer skills. Annual reports for the Gateway and Careers in Research for Minority Scholars programs are also included, along with documentation of the Women in Polymer Science and Engineering, and Minority Women in Management and Technical Fields programs. Publications and manuscripts include some of Kramer’s work on developmental psychology and psycholinguistics, including a bound copy of her master’s thesis. The collection also includes a black and white photographic print of Kramer, original drawings used in research, and an issue of the Polytechnic Reporter with an article about her death.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged into three series:
I. Biographical Information and Vita II. Publication and Manuscripts III. Research and Grant Projects
Folders within series are arranged by subject, chronologically.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research without restrictions.
Careers in Research for Minority Scholars in Materials Science.; National Science Foundation (U.S.).; Polytechnic University (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; United States. Office of Naval Research.; Annual reports; Correspondence; Developmental psychology; Engineering; Grant proposals; Masters theses; Minority college students; Minority graduate students; Psycholinquistics; Publications; Social sciences; Social Sciences -- Research; Women college students; Women engineering students; Women in the social sciences
- Series I: Biographical Information and Vita, 1978-1999 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains documents concerning Kramer's career, and her death in 1999. Specifically, folder 1 includes a black and white photo of Kramer, two iterations of her CV (one from the late 1970s, and another from the mid 1990s), a brief biographical sketch, an issue of the Polytechnic Reporter with news of her death, and correspondence with the New York Times concerning her obituary. Folder two contains all of the documentation regarding her appointment to full professor in 1996, including her application and letters of reference from colleagues.
  - Biographical Information, 1978-1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Full Professor Appointment, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II: Publications and Manuscripts, 1970-1994 (Box 1)
  - Masters Thesis, Tufts University, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Original Research and Reprints, 1980- unknown (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Original Drawings, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Women in Technology, 1982- 1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series III: Research and Grant Projects, 1978-1998 (Box 2)
  - Subseries A: Women in Science, 1978-1985
    - Women in Polymer Science, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Minority Women in Management and Technical Fields, 1979- 1982 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Helping Minority Girls Acquire Skills in Computers, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Subseries B: Careers in Research for Minority Scholars (CRMS), 1993-1998
    - CRMS, 1993- 1998 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - CRMS Annual Reports, 1993-1998 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Subseries C: Elementary and Junior High School Education, 1984-1995
    - Museum and University Based Learning, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Junior Academy, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Subseries D: Gateway Program, 1994-1997
    - Gateway, 1994- 1995 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Gateway, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 9)